RG 068, Film and Video
Connecticut State Library
Film and video collection
1919-1999
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut State Library (collector)
9.75 cubic feet
This is an artificial record group comprised of films and videos. Topics range from Connecticut Governors to various Connecticut history subjects.
RG068
Multiple
Scope and Content
This collection contains films and videos on various Connecticut history subjects. Included are the State Bureau of Aeronautics, 1933; film in which Governors Cross, Baldwin, and Lodge speak; a SNET film on the need for telephones during World War II; a film about the tobacco industry sponsored by a now defunct growers’ association; unedited television footage of the death and funeral of Governor Ella T. Grasso; and unedited footage of various tourist sites in Connecticut.
All 16mm films have been transferred to BETA SP masters and VHS cassettes. The 16mm and 35mm films along with Beta tapes are stored at the Connecticut State Library's Records Center in Rocky Hill.
Index Terms
Persons:
Babbidge, Homer D; Baldwin, Raymond E. (Raymond Earl), 1893-1986; Cross, Wilbur L. (Wilbur Lucius), 1862-1948; Dempsey, John, 1915-; Grasso, Ella; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973; Lodge, John Davis, 1903-1985
Subjects:
Aeronautics -- Connecticut; African Americans -- Medicine; Colt firearms -- Museums -- Connecticut -- Hartford; Connecticut State Library; Connecticut. Supreme Court; Connecticut Veterans' Home (Rocky Hill, Conn.); Constitutional conventions -- Connecticut; Hartford Circus File, Hartford, Conn., 1944; Indians of North America -- Medicine; Mansfield Training School (Mansfield Depot, Conn.); New York World's Fair (1939-1940); Sikorsky aircraft -- Exhibitions; Tobacco -- Connecticut -- History; Tobacco -- Connecticut River Valley -- History; United States Constitution Bicentennial, 1987-1991; World War, 1914-1918 -- Armistices -- Anniversaries, etc; World War, 1939-1945 -- War work -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Acetate films; Betacam-SP; DVDs; Motion pictures (visual works); 16mm; Videocassettes; VHS (TM)
Restrictions on Access
Some of these records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
In 1938, Commissioner of Aeronautics Charles L. Morris deposited two original reels, titled Flight which was produced in 1933, with the Connecticut State Library in exchange for copies. Morris also deposited a script he had written and was revised up to April 1, 1938.
Governor Wilbur Cross Meets with His Cabinet for the Last Time was deposited in the Connecticut State Library in January 1939.
Connecticut Answers was acquired by the Connecticut State Library either on November 30, 1945 or January 10, 1946.
Editorials: Connecticut Constitution was acquired by the Connecticut State Library in 1966.
Governor Raymond E. Baldwin, Jr. Reviews the Accomplishments of His Administration was acquired by the Connecticut State Library in 1941.
American Heritage was acquired by the Connecticut State Library in June 1957.
Tobacco Valley: The Story of Shade Grown Tobacco was acquired by the Connecticut State Library in 1972.
Connecticut Constitutional Convention 1965 was acquired by the Connecticut State Library in 1966.
Governor Baldwin of Connecticut was acquired by the Connecticut State Library in 1984.
WICC-TV in Bridgeport sent the reel of Governor John Lodge to the state capitol in 1954. It was acquired by the Connecticut State Library in 1989.
In Memoriam: Governor Ella T. Grasso Tapes #1-6 (Connecticut Mourns the Death of Governor Ella T. Grasso) were acquired by the Connecticut State Library on April 29, 1981.
Connecticut-Something Old-Something New by Joseph A. Fiorelli was acquired by the Connecticut State Library on September 2, 2010.
Connecticut State Veterans' Home & Hospital 125th anniversary was acquired by the Connecticut State Library in 2011.
Container List
- Inventory, 1919-1992
  - T003300
    - A grand restoration, undated; 1 videocassette (VHS): 1/2 in. (Box 1)
    - African and Native American medicine in early New England, 1992; 1 videocassette + supplemental material (VHS): 2nd ed., 1/2 in. (Box 1)
      Also contains report of how the film was made and list of works used.
      Created for History Day contest at Fox Middle School, Hartford Conn.
    - Bill of Rights TV commercials, undated; 1 videocassette (VHS): 4 min., 15 sec., 1/2 in. (Box 1)
      Produced by Philip Morris.
    - Constitution plaques presentation, 1989 July 17; 1 videocassette (VHS): 5 min., 46 sec., 1/2 in. (Box 1)
      Produced by Strong Arts Inc.
    - Constitutional symposium #1-2, undated; 2 videocassettes (VHS): 1/2 in. (Box 1)
    - Connecticut State Library flood - News coverage, 1989 December 2; 1 videocassette (VHS): 1/2 in. (Box 1)
    - Flight (reels 1 & 2), 1933; 4 videocassettes + supplemental material (VHS): silent, b & w, 1/2 in. (Box 1)
      Also contains 2 copies of a script to the film.
      Transferred from Beta SP master in August 2001 from Northeast Historic Film.
      Connecticut State Library holds 16mm film and Betacam SP L formats for this item.
    - Hartford collection, Hartford Public Library, undated; 1 videocassette (VHS): 1/2 in. (Box 1)
      Homemade copy.
    - President L.B. Johnson address during Governor Dempsey campaign, undated; 1 videocassette (VHS): 2 hr., 40 min., 1/2 in. (Box 1)
      Made by the Connecticut Network (CT-N).
      Looped film transfer.
    - Ratification convention, 1988 January 9; 1 videocassette (VHS, slow speed): 4 min., 15 sec., 1/2 in. (Box 1)
    - 3 CT Car III, undated; 1 videocassette (U-matic): 3/4 in. (Box 1)
      "Babbidge" is also written on the videocassette.
    - We the people - A staged reading at Christ Episcopal Church, Stratford, Conn., 1987 September 17; 1 videocassette + supplemental material (VHS SP): mono, 1/2 in. (Box 1)
      Also contains correspondence and projected budget for school touring company of We The People from Steven Otfinoski to Janet Crook, Executive Director, U.S. Constitution Bicentennial Commission of Connecticut, 10/28/1987.
      Books & lyrics by Steven Otfinoski. Music by Richard Amend & Mary Lang.
    - General Assembly, 1988 April 28; 1 videocassette (VHS): 1/2 in. (Box 1)
      Produced by Connecticut Public Television.
    - General Assembly, 1988 April 29; 1 videocassette (U-matic): 3/4 in. (Box 1)
    - A bicentennial celebration - We the people, 1987 June 16; 1 videocassette + supplemental material (U-matic): 60 min., 3/4 in. (Box 2)
      Also contains papers regarding the contents of the videocassette and a list in sequence of constitutional signers that appear on the videocassette.
      Produced by the United States Army.
    - Homer Babbidge-Reflections, 1984 April 9; 1 videocassette (U-matic): 58 min., 49 sec., 3/4 in. (Box 2)
    - Constitution signers series part 1, 1987; 1 videocassette (U-matic): 3/4 in. (Box 2)
    - Hartford Circus Fire: Her name is Eleanor, undated; 1 videocassette (VHS): 1/2 in. (Box 2)
      Produced by WFSB-TV, Hartford, Conn.
    - Hartford Circus Fire investigation: March 8-12, 1991, undated; 1 videocassette (VHS): 1/2 in. (Box 2)
    - 1965 Constitutional Convention NY, Boston series, 1992 January 9; 1 videocassette (VHS): 1/2 in. (Box 2)
    - Presidents; The 26th Amendment; Don't forget; Don't forget (news show), 1987 February 18; 1 videocassette (U-matic): 3/4 in. (Box 2)
      Produced by the Advertising Council/U.S. Constitution.
    - Reception and proceedings on the renaming of the museum, Memorial Hall (Baldwin reception), 1938 January 20; 1 videocassette (U-matic): col., 3/4 in. (Box 2)
    - Sikorsky exhibit at the State Library, 1982 March 18; 1 videocassette (U-matic): 3/4 in. (Box 2)
      Produced by P.M. Magazine Ch. 3.
    - State Supreme Court coverage - 1st day of 1 year experiment with allowing cameras in the courtroom, 1982 June 1; 1 videocassette (U-matic): col., 3/4 in. (Box 2)
      Produced by WVIT-TV Channel 30, Hartford, Conn. and WFSB-TV Channel 3, Hartford, Conn.
    - The Connecticut State Library - What's it all about?, circa 1984; 1 videocassette (U-matic): col., 4 min., 44 sec., 3/4 in. (Box 2)
    - We the people - A bicentennial celebration, undated; 1 videocassette (U-matic): 19 min., 48 sec., 3/4 in. (Box 2)
    - Connecticut Constitutional Convention 1965, 4 videocassettes (VHS): sd., b & w, 1/2 in. (Box 3)
      Segments shot by WHNB-TV in New Britain of the convention itself and activities leading up to the convention. Script sequence and sequence on film are not synchronized.
      Transferred from 16mm film.
    - Editorials: Connecticut Constitution, 1965 December; 4 videocassettes (VHS): sd., b & w, 1/2 in. (Box 3)
      Contains two 60 second editorials read by WNHC station manager. One editorial urges viewers to vote yes on Proposal 1, giving greater representation in the State Senate. The other editorial pertains to eminent domain compensation. Description of contents is from Connecticut Public Television which viewed the film.
      Produced by WNHC-TV film department in New Haven, Conn.
      Connecticut State Library holds 16mm film and Betacam SP S formats for this item.
    - Governor John Dempsey gubernatorial campaign of 1966, circa 1964-1966; 12 videocassettes (VHS): 1/2 in. (Box 3)
      Videocassettes are numbered 1-3. There are 4 copies of each.
    - Mansfield Training School: Chicago Special Olympics, 1968; 1 videocassette (VHS): 1/2 in. (Box 3)
    - Mansfield Training School: 50th Anniversary Parade, 1967; 1 videocassette (VHS): 1/2 in. (Box 3)
    - Mansfield Training School: 4th of July Parade, 1968; 1 videocassette (VHS): 1/2 in. (Box 3)
    - Mansfield Training School: Mrs. Kelly Parades, 1967-1968; 1 videocassette (VHS): 1/2 in. (Box 3)
    - Governor John Lodge, 1952; 4 videocassettes (VHS): 1/2 in. (Box 4)
    - In memoriam: Governor Ella T. Grasso (Connecticut mourns the death of Governor Ella T. Grasso), 1981 February 6-9; 18 videocassettes (VHS): sd., 1/2 in. (Box 4)
      Produced by WVIT-TV, Channel 30, Hartford 6 p.m. news.
      Transferred from 3/4 in. master by Northeast Historic Film.
      Videocassettes are numbered 1-6. There are 3 copies of each number.
      Connecticut State Library holds U-matic and Betacam SP L formats for this item.
    - American heritage, 1957 March 7; 4 videocassettes (VHS): sd., b & w, 1/2 in., 13 min., 30 sec. (Box 5)
      Documents the transfer of Colt Museum to the State of Connecticut in 1957 by the Penn-Texas Co. Includes also segments on Samuel Colt, the inside at the factory, and the transfer ceremony in Memorial Hall, Connecticut State Library Building on March 7, 1957.
    - Connecticut answers, circa 1945; 4 videocassettes (VHS): sd., b & w, 1/2 in. (Box 5)
      Includes great images of Connecticut industry in World War II.
      Film produced by SNET and narrated by Lowell Thomas.
      Connecticut State Library holds 16mm film format for this item.
    - Governor Baldwin of Connecticut (reels 1 & 2), circa 1941; 1 videocassette (VHS): 1/2 in. (Box 5)
      Developed by Worcester Film Corp., Worcester, MA.
      Transferred from Beta SP master in August 2001 by Northeast Historic Film.
    - Governor Raymond E. Baldwin, Jr. reviews the accomplishments of his administration, 1941 January 7; 4 videocassettes (VHS): sd., b & w, 1/2 in. (Box 5)
      January 7th was the day before the inauguration of Baldwin's successor, Robert Hurley.
      May also include remarks by unidentified state officials.
      Connecticut State Library holds 16mm film for this item.
    - Governor Wilbur Cross meets with his cabinet for the last time, 1938 December 9; 4 videocassettes (VHS): sd., b & w, 1/2 in. (Box 5)
      Governor Cross reads the 1938 Thanksgiving Proclamation and reviews accomplishments of his administration.
    - Tobacco valley: The story of shade grown tobacco, circa 1940s; 4 videocassettes (VHS): sd., col., 1/2 in. (Box 5)
      Narrated by Lowell Thomas. Produced by the Shade Tobacco Growers Agricultural Association in Windsor, CT which no longer exists.
    - Victory celebration in Litchfield, Conn., 1919 July 4; 1 videocassette (VHS): 1/2 in. (Box 5)
      Transferred by Northeast Historic Film.
    - New York World's Fair, 1940; 1 film roll, col., 35mm (Box Records Center)
      This item is stored at the Records Center.
  - 1984-009B
    - On the road: '76 Conn., undated; 1 reel, 5 in., 16mm (Box Records Center)
      Produced by CBS News.
  - 2011-020
    - Connecticut-Something old-Something new, 1967; 1 reel + supplemental material, 10.5 in., sd., col., 16mm (Box Records Center)
      Supplemental material includes the original certificate of honors for the film from the Connecticut Educational Film Library Association (EFLA) in 1968; the original black and white proof sheets for the film; copy of certificate of participation awarded to Fiorelli Films, Inc. for the film Micralign 140 by the Connecticut Film Festival on November 18, 1978; and Joseph A. Fiorelli's dossier listing credentials and awards with a photograph of the film maker.
      Produced by Joseph A. Fiorelli.
  - 2011-124
    - Connecticut State Veterans' Home & Hospital 125th anniversary, 1989; 1 videocassette + 1 DVD (Box 4)
      This item is stored with Accession T003300.
  - 2013-002
    - Raw video footage of Connecticut used to create "Discover America", circa 1990-1999; 8 DVD, 4.78 GB, 7 hr.
      Produced by The Learning Network (TLN) Productions, Inc.
      - Foxwood, circa 1990-1999; 1 DVD, 142 MB, 1 hr., 1 min., 25 sec. (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Foxwood v 2, circa 1990-1999; 1 DVD, 232 MB, 29 min., 35 sec. (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - CT Valley Railroad, circa 1990-1999; 1 DVD, 2.86 GB, 1 hr., 35 min., 06 sec. (Box 6, Folder 3)
        Includes unedited interview with Jeffrey A. Richards, President of Valley Railroad Company (Connecticut Valley Line) starting at 36 min., 20 sec. to 42 min., 20 sec.
      - CT Valley, circa 1990-1999; 1 DVD, 406 MB, 1 hr., 7 min., 33 sec. (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Southeastern Connecticut, circa 1990-1999; 1 DVD, 419 MB, 1 hr., 2 min. (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Southeastern Connecticut v. 2, circa 1990-1999; 1 DVD, 141 MB, 1 hr., 0 min., 45 sec. (Box 6, Folder 6)
        Includes unedited interview with William B. Stanley, Historian, starting at 41 min., 10 sec. to 44 min., 21 sec.
      - Greater Hartford, circa 1990-1999; 1 DVD, 305 MB, 47 min., 14 sec. (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Greater Hartford v. 2, circa 1990-1999; 1 DVD, 275 MB, 55 min., 40 sec. (Box 6, Folder 8)
        Includes unedited interview with Deirdre Bibby starting at 22 min., 22 sec. to 29 min., 12 sec.
        Includes unedited interview with John Boyer, Executive Director of Mark Twain House, starting at 41 min., 11 sec. to 42 min., 04 sec.